<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Michael Stapelbergs Website: posts tagged kinx</title>
  <link href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/tags/kinx/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/tags/kinx/"/>


  <id>https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/tags/kinx/</id>
  <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[kinX: latency measurement]]></title>
    <link href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-latency-measurement/"/>
    <id>https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-latency-measurement/</id>
    <published>2018-04-17T17:51:00+02:00</published>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>This post is part of a <a href="/posts/2018-04-17-kinx">series of posts about the kinX project</a>.</p>

<h3 id="latency-measurement">Latency measurement</h3>

<p>End-to-end latency consists of 3 parts:</p>

<ol>
<li>input latency (keyboard)</li>
<li>processing latency (computer)</li>
<li>output latency (monitor)</li>
</ol>

<p>During the development of the kinX keyboard controller, I realized that
measuring processing latency was quite simple with my hardware: I could start a
timer when sending a key press HID report to the computer and measure the
elapsed time when I would receive a reply from the computer.</p>

<p>The key to send is the Caps Lock key, because unlike other keys it results in a
reply: a HID report telling the keyboard to turn the Caps Lock LED on.</p>

<p><img src="/Bilder/kinx-latency-measurement-device.svg"></p>

<h3 id="measurement-device">Measurement device</h3>

<p>To make this measurement technique accessible to as many people as possible, I
decided to pull it out of my kinX keyboard controller and instead build it using
the FRDM-K66F evaluation board, which uses the same microcontroller.</p>

<p>The FRDM-K66F can be bought for about 60 USD at big electronics shops, e.g. Digi-Key.</p>

<p>Find the firmware at <a href="https://github.com/kinx-project/measure-fw">https://github.com/kinx-project/measure-fw</a></p>

<h3 id="baseline">Baseline</h3>

<p>To determine the lowest processing latency one can possibly get for userspace
applications on a Linux system, I wrote a small program which uses Linux’s evdev
API to receive key presses and react to a Caps Lock keypress as quickly as it
can by turning the Caps Lock LED on.</p>

<p>Find the program at <a href="https://github.com/kinx-project/measure-evdev">https://github.com/kinx-project/measure-evdev</a></p>

<p>The following layers are exercised when measuring this program:</p>

<ul>
<li>USB host controller</li>
<li>Linux kernel (USB and input subsystems)</li>
<li>input event API (evdev)</li>
</ul>

<p>Notably, graphical interfaces such as X11 or Wayland are excluded.</p>

<p>The measurements can be verified using Wireshark’s usbmon capturing, which
provides a view of the USB bus from the computer’s perspective, excluding USB
poll latency and USB transaction time.</p>

<p>Using Ubuntu 17.10, I measured a processing latency of 152 μs on average.</p>

<h3 id="emacs">Emacs</h3>

<p>Now let’s see whether my current editor of choice adds significant latency.</p>

<p>Using a few lines of Emacs Lisp, I instructed Emacs to turn on the Caps Lock LED
whenever a key is inserted into the current buffer. In combination with
remapping the Caps Lock key to any other key (e.g. “a”), this allows us to
measure Emacs’s processing latency.</p>

<p>On the same Ubuntu 17.10 installation used above, Emacs 25.2.2 adds on average
278 μs to the baseline processing latency.</p>

<p>Find the code at <a href="https://github.com/kinx-project/measure-emacs">https://github.com/kinx-project/measure-emacs</a></p>

<h3 id="end-to-end-latency">End-to-end latency</h3>

<p>With the kinX keyboard controller, we can achieve the following end-to-end latency:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>contributor</th>
<th>latency</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Matrix scan</td>
<td>≈ 208 μs</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>USB poll</td>
<td>≈ 125 μs</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Linux</td>
<td>≈ 152 μs</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Emacs</td>
<td>≈ 278 μs</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p><br>This sums up to ≈ 763 μs on average. On top of that, we have output latency
within [0, 16ms] due to the 60 Hz refresh rate of our monitors.</p>

<p>Note that using a compositor adds one frame of output latency.</p>

<h3 id="input-latency-perception">Input latency perception</h3>

<p>A natural question to ask is how well humans can perceive input latency. After
all, keyboards have been manufactured for many years, and if input latency was
really that important, surely manufacturers would have picked up on this fact by
now?</p>

<p>I ran a little unscientific experiment in the hope to further my understanding
of this question at the most recent Chaos Communication Congress in Leipzig.</p>

<p>In the experiment, I let 17 people play a game on a specially prepared
keyboard. In each round, the game reconfigures the keyboard to either have
additional input latency or not, decided at random. The player can then type a
few keys and make a decision. If the player can correctly indicate whether
additional input latency was present in more than 50% of the cases, the player
is said to be able to distinguish latency at that level. On each level, the game
decreases the additional input latency: it starts with 100ms, then 75ms, then
50ms, etc.</p>

<p>The most sensitive player reliably recognized an additional 15ms of input
latency.</p>

<p>Some players could not distinguish 75ms of additional input latency.</p>

<p>Every player could distinguish 100ms of additional input latency.</p>

<p>My take-away is that many people cannot perceive slight differences in input
latency at all, explaining why keyboard manufacturers don’t optimize for low
latency.</p>

<p>Reducing input latency still seems worthwhile to me: even if the reduction
happens under the threshold at which you can perceive differences in input
latency, it buys you more leeway in the entire stack. In other words, you might
now be able to turn on an expensive editor feature which previously slowed down
typing too much.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>When I started looking into input latency, my keyboard had dozens of
milliseconds of latency. I found an easy win in the old firmware, then hit a
wall, started the kinX project and eventually ended up with a keyboard with just
0.33ms input latency.</p>

<p>Even if I had not reduced the input latency of my keyboard at all, I feel that
this project was a valuable learning experience: I now know a lot more about PCB
design, ARM microcontrollers, USB, HID, etc.</p>

<p>Typing on a self-built keyboard feels good: be it because of the warm fuzzy
feeling of enjoying the fruits of your labor, or whether the input latency
indeed is lower, I’m happy with the result either way.</p>

<p>Lastly, I can now decidedly claim that the processing latency of modern
computers is perfectly fine (remember our 152 μs + 278 μs measurement for
Linux + Emacs), and as long as you pick decent peripherals, your end-to-end
latency will be fine, too.</p>

<h3 id="what-s-next">What’s next?</h3>

<p>By far the biggest factor in the end-to-end latency is the monitor’s refresh
rate, so getting a monitor with a high refresh rate and no additional processing
latency would be the next step in reducing the end-to-end latency.</p>

<p>As far as the keyboard goes, the matrix scan could be eliminated by wiring up
each individual key to a microcontroller with enough GPIO pins. The USB poll
delay could be eliminated by switching to USB 3, but I don’t know of any
microcontrollers which have USB 3 built-in yet. Both of these improvements are
likely not worth the effort.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[kinX: USB Hub]]></title>
    <link href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-usb-hub/"/>
    <id>https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-usb-hub/</id>
    <published>2018-04-17T17:50:00+02:00</published>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>This post is part of a <a href="/posts/2018-04-17-kinx">series of posts about the kinX project</a>.</p>

<h3 id="motivation">Motivation</h3>

<p>The Kinesis Advantage comes with a built-in 2-port USB hub. That hub uses a
proprietary connector to interface with a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PS/2_port">PS/2</a> keyboard controller, so it
cannot be used with a USB keyboard controller. As the built-in hub is the
natural place to connect the Logitech unified receiver dongle, not being able to
use the hub is mildly annoying.</p>

<p>The kinX MK66F keyboard controller presently needs two USB cables: one connected
to the USBFS port to supply the PCB with power and receive firmware updates (via
the Teensy bootloader chip), and one connected to the USBHS port for the actual
keyboard device.</p>

<p>Lastly, even if the original built-in USB hub had internal ports (instead of a
PS/2 converter), it only supports USB 1.1, nullifying any latency improvements.</p>

<p>Hence, I decided to build a drop-in replacement USB 2.0 hub with 2 external USB
ports and 2 internal USB ports, using the same proprietary connector as the
original, so that the original keyboard USB cable could be re-used.</p>

<h3 id="design-phase">Design phase</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, I could not find an open hardware USB 2.0 hub design on the
internet, so I started researching various USB hub chips. I quickly discarded
the idea of using USB 3 due to its much stricter requirements.</p>

<p>In the end, I decided to go with the Cypress HX2VL series because of their
superior documentation: I found a detailed data sheet, an evaluation board, the
associated schematics, design checklist/guidelines, and even the evaluation
board’s bill of materials.</p>

<p>This is what the finished build of my design looks like:</p>
















<a href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-usb-hub/kinx-hub.jpg"><img
  srcset="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-usb-hub/kinx-hub_hub171d3553dfb50fbddf8778151525534_430879_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 2x,https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-usb-hub/kinx-hub_hub171d3553dfb50fbddf8778151525534_430879_1800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 3x"
  src="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-usb-hub/kinx-hub_hub171d3553dfb50fbddf8778151525534_430879_600x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  alt="kinX USB Hub" title="kinX USB Hub"
  width="600"
  height="512"
  style="border: 1px solid #000"
  
  loading="lazy"></a>




<h3 id="power">Power</h3>

<p>After completing my first build, I tested a few USB devices with my hub. The
Logitech unified receiver dongle and the
<a href="https://www.yubico.com/start/">YubiKey</a> worked fine. However, my external hard
drive and my USB memory stick did not work. In the syslog, I would see:</p>

<pre><code>kernel: usb 1-14.4.4: rejected 1 configuration due to insufficient available bus power
</code></pre>

<p>This is because the USB specification limits bus-powered hubs to 100mA per
port. While high power usage does not come as a surprise for the external hard
disk, it turns out that even my USB memory stick requires 200mA. This was a
surprise, because that stick works on other, commercial bus-powered USB hubs.</p>

<p>A closer look reveals that all 3 commercial USB hubs I have tested claim to be
self-powered (i.e. using an external power supply), even though they are
not. This way, the kernel’s power limitation is circumvented, and up to 500mA
can be used per port. In practice, the host port only supplies 500mA, so the
user must be careful not to plug in devices which require more than 500mA in
aggregate.</p>

<p>I changed the SELFPWR configuration pin to have my hub claim it was
self-powered, too, and that made all USB devices I tested work fine.</p>

<h3 id="eeprom-programming">EEPROM programming</h3>

<p>When debugging the power issue, I originally thought the Maximum Power setting
in the hub’s USB device descriptor needed to be raised. This turned out to not
be correct: the Maximum Power refers to the power which the hub uses for its own
circuitry, not the power it passes through to connected devices.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, it’s a nice touch to modify the device descriptor to put in a
custom vendor name, product name and serial number: that way, the device shows
up with a recognizable name in your syslog or
<a href="https://manpages.debian.org/stretch/usbutils/lsusb.8"><code>lsusb(8)</code></a> output, and
udev rules can be used to apply settings based on the serial number.</p>

<p>To modify the device descriptor, an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EEPROM">EEPROM (electrically erasable programmable
read-only memory)</a> needs to be added to
the design, from which the HX2VL will read configuration.</p>

<p>The HX2VL allows field-programming of the connected EEPROM, i.e. writing to it
via the USB hub chip. I found the Windows-only tool hard to set up on a modern
Windows installation, so I wondered whether I could build a simpler to use tool.</p>

<p>Under the covers, the tool merely sends commands with the vendor-specific
request code 14 via USB, specifying an index of the two-byte word to
read/write. This can be replicated in a few lines of Go:</p>

<pre><code>dev, _ := usb.OpenDeviceWithVIDPID(0x04b4, 0x6570)
eepromRequest := 14
wIndex := 0 // [0, 63] for 128 bytes of EEPROM
dev.Control(gousb.RequestTypeVendor|0x80, 
  eepromRequest, 0, wIndex, make([]byte, 2))
</code></pre>

<p>The EEPROM contents are well-described in the <a href="http://www.cypress.com/file/114101/download">HX2VL data
sheet</a>, so the rest is easy.</p>

<p>See <a href="https://github.com/kinx-project/mk66f-blaster">https://github.com/kinx-project/mk66f-blaster</a> for the tool.</p>

<h3 id="lessons-learnt">Lessons learnt</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>If possible, design the PCB in such a way that components you think you don’t
need (e.g. the EEPROM) can optionally be soldered on. This would have saved me
a PCB design/fabrication cycle.</p></li>

<li><p>Get the evaluation board to figure out the configuration you need
(e.g. self-powered vs. bus-powered).</p></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="next-up">Next up</h3>

<p>The <a href="/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-latency-measurement/">last post introduces the processing latency measurement firmware for the
FRDM-K66F development board</a> and
draws a conclusion.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[kinX: keyboard controller with &lt;0.33ms input latency]]></title>
    <link href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-keyboard-controller/"/>
    <id>https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-keyboard-controller/</id>
    <published>2018-04-17T17:49:00+02:00</published>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>This post is part of a <a href="/posts/2018-04-17-kinx">series of posts about the kinX project</a>.</p>

<h3 id="background">Background</h3>

<p>10 years ago I got a Kinesis Advantage keyboard. I wrote about the experience of
learning to touch-type using the ergonomic <a href="https://neo-layout.org/">NEO layout</a>
in my (German) post <a href="/posts/2009-01-01-neo_kinesis/">“Neo-Layout auf einer
Kinesis-Tastatur”</a>.</p>

<p>The Kinesis Advantage is still the best keyboard I’ve ever used, and I use one
every day, both at the office and at home.</p>

<p>I had two reasons to start modifying the keyboard:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>I prefer Cherry MX blue key switches over the Cherry MX brown key switches
the Kinesis comes with. Nowadays, you can get a Kinesis with Cherry MX red
key switches, which felt okay in a quick test.</p></li>

<li><p>The original keyboard controller has (had?) a bug where modifier keys such as
Shift would get stuck at least once a week: you would press Shift, press A,
release A, release Shift, press A and see AA instead of Aa.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>I solved issue ① with the help of the excellent Kinesis technical support, who
sold me unpopulated PCBs so that I could solder on my own key switches.</p>

<p>Issue ② was what lead to my first own keyboard controller build, which I
documented in <a href="/posts/2013-03-21-kinesis_custom_controller/">“Hacking your own Kinesis keyboard
controller”</a> (2013).</p>

<p>Then, the topic of input latency popped into my filter bubble, with excellent
 posts such as <a href="https://pavelfatin.com/typing-with-pleasure/">Pavel Fatin’s “Typing with
pleasure”</a>. I started wondering
what input latency I was facing, and whether/how I could reduce it.</p>

<p>Given that I was using a custom keyboard controller, it was up to me to answer
that question. After trying to understand and modify the firmware I had been
using for the last 4 years, I realized that I first needed to learn much more
about how keyboards work.</p>

<p>I firmly believe that creating a good environment is vital for development,
especially for intrinsically-motivated side projects like this one. Hence, I set
the project aside until a colleague gifted me his old Kinesis which had
intermittent issues. I removed the electronics and started using that keyboard
as my development keyboard.</p>

<h3 id="sources-of-input-latency">Sources of input latency</h3>

<p>A keyboard controller has 3 major tasks:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>matrix scan</strong>: to avoid physically connecting every single key switch
directly to a microcontroller (requiring a large number of GPIO pins), most
keyboards use a matrix. See <a href="http://blog.komar.be/how-to-make-a-keyboard-the-matrix/">“How to make a keyboard — the
matrix”</a> for a good
explanation.</p></li>

<li><p><strong>debouncing</strong>: when pressing a key switch, it doesn’t cleanly change from a
low voltage level to a high voltage level (or vice-versa). Instead, it
bounces: the voltage level rapidly oscillates until it eventually reaches a
stable steady state. Because one key press shouldn’t result in a whole bunch
of characters, keyboard controllers need to debounce the key press.</p></li>

<li><p><strong>USB</strong>: nowadays, keyboards use USB (for example to be compatible with
laptops, which generally don’t have PS/2 ports), so the keyboard’s state needs
to be communicated to the computer via USB.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>Here’s an illustration of the timing of a key press being handled by a naive
keyboard controller implementation:</p>

<p><img src="/Bilder/kinx-input-latency-sources.svg"></p>

<p>In the worst case, a key press happens just after a keyboard matrix scan. The
first source of latency is the time it takes until the next keyboard matrix scan
happens.</p>

<p>Depending on the implementation, the key press now sits in a data structure,
waiting for the debounce time to pass.</p>

<p>Finally, once the key press was successfully debounced, the device must wait
until the USB host polls it before it can send the HID report.</p>

<p>Unless the matrix scan interval is coupled to the USB poll interval, the delays
are additive, and the debounce time is usually constant: in the best case, a key
press happens just before a matrix scan (0ms) and gets debounced (say, 5ms) just
before a USB poll (0ms).</p>

<h3 id="teensy-3-6-controller-for-learning">Teensy 3.6 controller (for learning)</h3>

<p>My old keyboard controller used the
<a href="https://www.pjrc.com/teensy/index.html">Teensy++</a>, which is fairly dated at
this point. I decided a good start of the project would be to upgrade to the
current Teensy 3.6, cleaning up the schematics on the way.</p>

<p><img src="/Bilder/kinx-teensy36.jpg" width="100%"></p>

<p>To ensure I understand all involved parts, I implemented a bare-metal firmware
almost from scratch: I cobbled together the required startup code, USB stack
and, most importantly, key matrix scanning code.</p>

<p>In my firmware, the Teensy 3.6 runs at 180 MHz (compared to the Teensy++’s 16
MHz) and scans the keyboard matrix in a busy loop (as opposed to on USB
poll). Measurements confirmed a matrix scan time of only 208μs (0.2ms).</p>

<aside class="admonition note">
  <div class="note-container">
    <div class="note-icon">
      <svg id="exclamation-icon" width="100%" height="100%" viewBox="0 0 24 24" version="1.1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:space="preserve" style="fill-rule:evenodd;clip-rule:evenodd;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:1.41421;">
    <path d="M0,0L24,0L24,24L0,24L0,0Z" style="fill:none;"/>
    <g transform="matrix(1.2,0,0,1.2,-2.4,-2.4)">
        <path d="M12,2C6.48,2 2,6.48 2,12C2,17.52 6.48,22 12,22C17.52,22 22,17.52 22,12C22,6.48 17.52,2 12,2ZM13,17L11,17L11,15L13,15L13,17ZM13,13L11,13L11,7L13,7L13,13Z" style="fill-rule:nonzero;"/>
    </g>
</svg>

    </div>
    <div class="admonition-content"><strong>Update:</strong> Previously, I had measured the matrix scan time as 100μs
(0.1ms). While that is technically correct, in practice, matrix scans take
longer due to interrupts, so the new 208μs measurement is more realistic.</div>
  </div>
</aside>


<p>I implemented debouncing the way it is described in <a href="https://summivox.wordpress.com/2016/06/03/keyboard-matrix-scanning-and-debouncing/">Yin Zhong’s “Keyboard
Matrix Scanning and
Debouncing”</a>:
by registering a key press/release on the rising/falling edge and applying the
debounce time afterwards, effectively eliminating debounce latency.</p>

<p>Note that while the Cherry MX datasheet specifies a debounce time of 5ms, I
found it necessary to increase the time to 10ms to prevent bouncing in some of
my key switches, which are already a few years old.</p>

<p>I set the USB device descriptor’s poll interval to 1, meaning poll every 1 USB
micro frame, which is 1ms long with USB 1.x (Full Speed).</p>

<p>This leaves us at an input latency within [0ms, 1.1ms]:</p>

<ul>
<li>≤ 0.2ms scan latency</li>
<li>0ms debounce latency</li>
<li>≤ 1ms USB poll latency</li>
</ul>

<p>Can we reduce the input latency even further? The biggest factor is the USB poll
interval.</p>

<h3 id="usb-high-speed">USB High Speed</h3>

<p>With USB 2.0 High Speed, the micro frame duration is reduced to 125μs
(0.125ms). The NXP MK66F micro controller in the Teensy 3.6 has two USB ports:</p>

<ol>
<li>the Full Speed-only USBFS port, which is used by the Teensy 3.6</li>
<li>the High Speed-capable USBHS port, which the Teensy optionally uses for host
mode, with experimental software support (at the time of writing)</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/Bilder/kinx-usbhs-breakout.jpg" width="100%"></p>

<p>While the software support was a road block which could conceivably be solved, I
also faced a mechanical problem: the available space in the Kinesis keyboard and
the position of the USB High Speed port pins on the Teensy 3.6 unfortunately
prevented installing any sort of breakout board to actually use the port.</p>

<p>I decided to move from the Teensy 3.6 to my own design with the same
microcontroller.</p>

<h3 id="mk66f-keyboard-controller">MK66F keyboard controller</h3>
















<a href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-keyboard-controller/kinx-mk66f.jpg"><img
  srcset="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-keyboard-controller/kinx-mk66f_huadaad7ed50f8d38b8cbe347b2c1948f3_1364992_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 2x,https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-keyboard-controller/kinx-mk66f_huadaad7ed50f8d38b8cbe347b2c1948f3_1364992_1800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 3x"
  src="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-keyboard-controller/kinx-mk66f_huadaad7ed50f8d38b8cbe347b2c1948f3_1364992_600x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  alt="MK66F" title="MK66F"
  width="600"
  height="469"
  style="border: 1px solid #000"
  
  loading="lazy"></a>




<p>To make development pleasant, I connected a USB-to-serial adapter (to UART0) and
a “rebootor” (to PROGHEAD): another Teensy with a special firmware to trigger
programming mode. This way, I could set my editor’s <code>compile-command</code> to <code>make
&amp;&amp; teensy_loader_cli -r …</code>, compiling the code, uploading and booting into the
resulting firmware with a single keyboard shortcut.</p>

<p>I based the firmware for this controller on NXP’s SDK examples, to ensure I get
a well-tested and maintained USB stack for the USBHS port. I did some
measurements to confirm the stack does not add measurable extra latency, so I
did not see any value in me maintaining a custom USB stack.</p>

<p>The firmware can be found at <a href="https://github.com/kinx-project/mk66f-fw">https://github.com/kinx-project/mk66f-fw</a></p>

<p>The hardware can be found at <a href="https://github.com/kinx-project/mk66f-hw">https://github.com/kinx-project/mk66f-hw</a></p>

<p>Using USB 2.0 High Speed leaves us at an input latency within [0ms, 0.33ms]:</p>

<ul>
<li>≤ 0.2ms scan latency</li>
<li>0ms debounce latency</li>
<li>≤ 0.125ms USB poll latency</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="lessons-learnt">Lessons learnt</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>In the future, I will base custom designs on the vendor’s development board
(instead of on the Teensy). This way, the vendor-provided code could be used
without any modifications.</p></li>

<li><p>While the Teensy bootloader means getting started with the microcontroller
just requires a USB port, using a JTAG connector for development would be more
powerful: not only does it replace the combination of Teensy bootloader,
serial and rebootor, but it also supports debugging with gdb.</p></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="next-up">Next up</h3>

<p>The <a href="/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-usb-hub/">second post motivates and describes building a drop-in replacement USB
hub</a> for the Kinesis Advantage keyboard.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[kinX: overview]]></title>
    <link href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx/"/>
    <id>https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2018-04-17-kinx/</id>
    <published>2018-04-17T17:48:00+02:00</published>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The kinX project is described in a series of blog posts:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>While not strictly a part of this series, <a href="/posts/2013-03-21-kinesis_custom_controller/">“Hacking your own Kinesis keyboard
controller”</a> describes the first
controller I built in 2013 (maybe interesting for context).</p></li>

<li><p>The <a href="/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-keyboard-controller/">first post introduces the kinX, a keyboard
controller</a> with merely 0.33ms of
input latency (including USB).</p></li>

<li><p>The <a href="/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-usb-hub/">second post motivates and describes building a drop-in replacement USB
hub</a> for the Kinesis Advantage keyboard.</p></li>

<li><p>The <a href="/posts/2018-04-17-kinx-latency-measurement/">last post introduces the processing latency measurement firmware for the
FRDM-K66F development board</a> and
draws a conclusion.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>You can find the project’s artifacts at <a href="https://github.com/kinx-project">https://github.com/kinx-project</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
